Donald A. Wollheim Papers
Donald A. Wollheim Papers
1959-1969
Wollheim, Donald A.
1.25 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, science fiction writer (1914-1990). Collection contains typescript manuscripts for fiction and non-fiction works, primarily novels in his Mike Mars series.
148761
Biographical History
Donald A. Wollheim (1914-1990) was an award-winning science fiction writer, editor, publisher, and fan. Wollheim's first story was published when he was nineteen, and despite his many other activities he continued to be published regularly for more than thirty years. He wrote under numerous pen names, including David Grinnell, Arthur Cooke, Millard Verne Gordon, Martin Pearson, Braxton Wells, Graham Conway, and Lawrence Woods. In addition to his writing, Wollheim the organizer of the first science fiction convention in 1936, publisher of numerous fanzines, and founder of the Fantasy Amateur Press Association. He was also a founding member of The Futurians, alongn with Isaac Asimov, Frederik Pohl, Cyril Kornbluth, James Blish, Damon Knight and many other notable names in science fiction.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Donald A. Wollheim Papers consists entirely of his writings, almost all in manuscript form. Most are novels in the Mike Mars series, published initially under the name David Grinnell.
Arrangement of the Collection
Manuscripts are subdivided into fiction and non-fiction, then arranged alphabetically by title.
Related Material
has numerous collections relating to science fiction and fantasy authors, editors, organizations, and events. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Science fiction; De Forest, Lee, 1873-1961.; Mars, Mike (Fictional character) -- Fiction.; Wollheim, Donald A.; Astronauts -- Fiction.; Authors, American.; Science fiction, American.; Space travel -- Fiction.; Books.; Manuscripts for publication.; Authors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Writings
  - Fiction
    - Destiny's orbit, 1961; first draft (Box 1)
    - Mike Mars, Astronaut [Mike Mars #1], 1959; first draft (Box 1)
    - Mike Mars, Astronaut [Mike Mars #1], setting copy, with edits and corrections; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Mike Mars at Cape Canaveral [Mike Mars #3], 1960; first draft (Box 1)
    - Mike Mars at Cape Canaveral [Mike Mars #3], setting copy, with edits and corrections; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Mike Mars in orbit [Mike Mars #4], 1960; first draft (Box 1)
    - Mike Mars in orbit [Mike Mars #4], setting copy, with edits and corrections; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Mike Mars flies the dyna-soar [Mike Mars #5], [1961]; first draft (Box 1)
    - Mike Mars flies the dyna-soar [Mike Mars #5], setting copy, with edits and corrections; has alternate title "Mike Mars' space rescue"; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Mike Mars, South Pole spaceman [Mike Mars #6], 1962; first draft; has alternate title "Mike Mars and the South Pole Rocket" (Box 2)
    - Mike Mars, South Pole spaceman [Mike Mars #6], setting copy, with edits and corrections; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Mike Mars and the mystery satellite [Mike Mars #7], 1962; first draft (Box 2)
    - Mike Mars and the mystery satellite [Mike Mars #7], setting copy, with edits and corrections; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Mike Mars around the moon [Mike Mars #8], 1963; first draft (Box 2)
    - Mike Mars around the moon [Mike Mars #8], illustrations and captions (Box 2)
    - Mike Mars around the moon [Mike Mars #8], setting copy pp. 1-75, with edits and corrections (Box 2)
    - Mike Mars around the moon [Mike Mars #8], setting copy pp. 76-123, with edits and corrections; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Two dozen dragon eggs, 1969; paperback edition, Powell Sci Fi (Box 3)
  - Non-fiction
    - The wizard of wireless [working title; published as Advancing the electronic age: Lee De Forest, typescript draft with edits and corrections (Box 3)